<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Heritage on Michael E. Nelson</title>
    <link>http://michaelnet.biz/tags/heritage/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Heritage on Michael E. Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://michaelnet.biz/tags/heritage/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Glambu-Launch Post</title>
      <link>http://michaelnet.biz/post/the-glambu-launch-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://michaelnet.biz/post/the-glambu-launch-post/</guid>
      <description>Question: What is the sum of the galleries, libraries, archives, and museums industry category‘s acronym (GLAM) and the archaic word ambulator (Noun, “One that walks about” - Lewis &amp;amp; Short, 1879)?
Answer: Glambulator, the name of my CHI project. Glambulator has launched, and it’s available at glambulator.matrix.msu.edu/.
 Entity Graph Tab   Glambulator is about exploring the CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model (CIDOC-CRM) and phenomena that have been annotated by it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing RDF Triples in an Engaging Way</title>
      <link>http://michaelnet.biz/post/visualizing-rdf-triples-in-an-engaging-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://michaelnet.biz/post/visualizing-rdf-triples-in-an-engaging-way/</guid>
      <description>The application that has taken shape since the beginning of the CHI fellowship executes queries against the British Museum’s (BM) SPARQL endpoint. The BM system returns results serialized as XML- or JSON-LD. The application updates its data store (Redux) and renders the collection of results as a simple list. This is straightforward enough. On the other hand, I’ve had to think a bit more about how to render single query results in response to user selection of any given list item.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Considering ICT-Mediated Humanities Collaboration: A Report from ACRL 2017</title>
      <link>http://michaelnet.biz/post/considering-ict-mediated-humanities-collaboration-a-report-from-acrl-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://michaelnet.biz/post/considering-ict-mediated-humanities-collaboration-a-report-from-acrl-2017/</guid>
      <description>Last week I was able to attend the annual conference for the Association of College and Research Libraries (ACRL) in Baltimore (proceedings here). One talk struck me as particularly relevant to cultural heritage informatics. The authors explored humanities scholarship collaboration across institutional and disciplinary boundaries, focusing on the fifteen institutions that constitute the Humanities Without Walls (HWW) consortium (which includes Michigan State). The authors reported the themes that emerged from qualitative analysis of semi-structured interview transcripts, and represented the resultant collaboration network as a network graph with dimensions including team-size per project, number of grant awardees per institution, and number of connections between projects and institutions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clarifying My Project’s Topic</title>
      <link>http://michaelnet.biz/post/clarifying-my-projects-topic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://michaelnet.biz/post/clarifying-my-projects-topic/</guid>
      <description>My project will consist of a deep dive into the representation of heritage objects in CIDOC-CRM and will result in an interactive presentation of case analyses of CIDOC-CRM object descriptions.
I’m interested in exploring the operations through which an object comes to be recognized as a heritage object. In documenting the why of the project, I’ve dabbled with the term &amp;lsquo;heritage industry&amp;rsquo;. But while I’ve found The heritage industry: Britain in a climate of decline (Hewison, 1987) pretty compelling, I’m not interested in what seems more like a particular argument’s foil to history, well executed, than a term with much analytic purchase here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>