<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sparql on Michael E. Nelson</title>
    <link>http://michaelnet.biz/tags/sparql/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sparql on Michael E. Nelson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://michaelnet.biz/tags/sparql/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Glambulator</title>
      <link>http://michaelnet.biz/project/glambulator/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://michaelnet.biz/project/glambulator/</guid>
      <description> Problem Solution [Source and Documentation] [Demo] Other Assets </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Querying the Collection of the British Museum for Propositional Objects</title>
      <link>http://michaelnet.biz/post/querying-the-collection-of-the-british-museum-for-propositional-objects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://michaelnet.biz/post/querying-the-collection-of-the-british-museum-for-propositional-objects/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned last month, one of the ideas of the semantic web is to render data from specialized, disparate sources comparable, and this is achieved by developing specifications like CIDOC-CRM. One implementation of CIDOC-CRM is the Erlangen CRM. Heritage institutions like the British Museum use implementations like this to organize their collection. It is implemented in the Web Ontology Language (OWL) and can be browsed in an ontology explorer like Protégé or by just reading the XML.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning About Web 3.0</title>
      <link>http://michaelnet.biz/post/learning-about-web-3-0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://michaelnet.biz/post/learning-about-web-3-0/</guid>
      <description>My project involves working with some of the technologies of the semantic web. The main idea of the semantic web (or web 3.0, and in Berners-Lee’s language the “read+write+execute” phase that will supersede the “read-only” phase of web 1.0 and the “read+write” phase of web 2.0) is for web services to reason automatically about resources. Robust descriptions enable the linking of heterogeneous resources. Semantic web services commonly use the Resource Description Framework (RDF) to represent entities in terms of subjects, objects, and predicates.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>